PART 2

In the first part of this series we looked at using the Raspberry Pi GPIO port as an input to
monitor the status of a switch. In this part we learn about outputs.

We use the term INPUT to refer to the fact that
the computer is being controlled in some way
by an external event, such as our previous experiment
where the computer responds to the
press of a switch. An OUTPUT is where the
computer is controlling or communicating with
the outside world.

You are perhaps used to thinking of things like
the screen and keyboard as being part of a
computer but they are in fact peripherals, extra
parts that make it possible for the computer to
communicate with the outside world. A computer
is just a collection of chips on a circuit
board that has very little use until it has a way
of communicating with the outside world, a
computer that can do nothing more than talk
to itself is of little use. Put some software on an
SD card and plug the power in and the Raspberry
Pi is a complete operating computer,
without a screen however we have no way of
knowing what it is doing. A screen is an output
device, an example of just one of the many
ways that a computer can provide an output.

As we learnt last time, computers are binary
so a computer communicates with the outside
world by switching things on and off. The image
you see on the screen is produced by the
computer switching the individual dots (pixels)
on and off on the screen. We are going to
have the Raspberry Pi control the LED on our
breadboard experiment from last time.

Circuit Description
We are making one small change to the circuit
from last time. We turn the resistor (R1) 90°
so it is connected to points E1 & E5, this disconnects
the LED from the switch. Instead we
connect a second GPIO pin to point D1 so that
the LED can be independently controlled.
When using the Raspberry Pi GPIO pins as an
output we have to be very careful not to draw
too much current. The 470Ω resistor in this
circuit limits the current to 3mA, just enough to
light a standard 3mm Red LED. ►

Python LED Test Program
Create a new text file named ledtest.py and
enter the following program.

#!/usr/bin/python
import time
import RPi.GPIO as GPIO
GPIO.setup(12, GPIO.OUT)
GPIO.output(12, False)
time.sleep(3)
GPIO.output(12, True)

Program Description
We start by including the time and RPi.GPIO
packages in our program so we can make use
of their functions by using import.
Next we configure GPIO pin 11 on the raspberry
Pi as an output.
Our program is a simple test, it sets pin 12 LOW
then waits 3 seconds before setting it HIGH.
This will switch the LED on for 3 seconds and
then off when the program ends. It might seem
a little odd that the LED lights up when we set
our output as FALSE. This is because one side
of our LED is connected to the 3.3V power, to
complete the circuit our GPIO pin has to be 0V.
When we set the value as TRUE our output is
set to 3.3V making both sides of the LED 3.3V
preventing a current flowing.

To start the program type the following command
into the terminal window.

sudo python ledtest.py

The sudo command is necessary as programs
that use the GPIO port require super user
privileges within the operating system.

Pushbutton Test Program

Now we can combine the input and outputs to
reconnect the LED to the switch in software.
Create a new file called pushbutton.py and
enter the following program.

#!/usr/bin/python
import RPi.GPIO as GPIO
GPIO.setup(11, GPIO.IN)
GPIO.setup(12, GPIO.OUT)
while True:
if GPIO.input(11):
GPIO.output(12, True)
else:
GPIO.output(12, False)

Program Description
We start by importing the RPi.GPIO package
and configuring GPIO pin 11 as an input and
pin 12 as an output using the now familiar
“GPIO.setup” syntax.
By using ‘while True’ we create a never ending
loop so that everything below this will be
repeated until we choose to stop it.
Our program keeps checking the status of pin
11 that will always be True (High) while the
button is not being pressed. As soon as the
button is pressed the GPIO pin goes low and
our result will be False: at which point we set
GPIO pin 12 to be false (Low) to light up the
LED.

When you have had enough press the
Control+C keys to stop the program.
Having the LED light up when the switch is
pressed is not terribly useful as it just gives us
the same result we had before when the LED
was directly connected to the switch, so let’s
make something a bit more interesting.

Electronic Die

Because the LED and switch are now independent
we have a great deal more flexibility.
We will now write a program that will flash a
random number between 1 and 6 when the
button is pressed.

#!/usr/bin/python
import RPi.GPIO as GPIO
import time
import random
GPIO.setup (11, GPIO.IN)
GPIO.setup (12, GPIO.OUT)
while True:
if not GPIO.input(11):
flash = random.randint(1,6)
while not GPIO.input(11):
GPIO.output(12,True)
while flash > 0:
GPIO.output(12, False)
time.sleep(.5)
GPIO.output(12, True)
time.sleep(.5)
flash -= 1
else:
GPIO.output(12,True)

Program Description
The program runs a continuous while loop
waiting for the button to be pressed. Once the
button press is detected we generate a random
integer value between 1 and 6. An integer
means a whole number rather than a floating
point number so we get numbers like 2 & 3
rather than 2.45678. Once the random number
has been generated we wait for the button
to be released before continuing to prevent
cheating.

When the button is released we enter a countdown
loop that flashes the LED and reduces
the count by 1 after each flash until it reaches
0. The program then returns to the main
loop where it waits for the next button
press to start the process again.

Conclusion

We have now covered the basics of how
to monitor an input and switch things on
and off using an output. With just this
simple set-up of 1 switch and 1 LED we
can already make something useful.

Why not try modifying the pushbutton.py
program so that the LED is on but goes
off when the button is pressed, there is
more than one way of doing it, can you
see two or more possibilities?

Many people have been asking about
how to control something that requires
more power than a small LED. In the next
instalment we will look at the various options
available. ●

This article is sponsored by Tandy.
All the components mentioned in this series and much more
are available from the new Tandy online shop. Many new
components being added daily.